University of Connecticut 1988.0014
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut, President's Office Records [Charles L. Beach 1908-1928]
undated, 1906-1929.
1988.0014
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
9.0 Linear feet
Charles Lewis Beach attended the University of Wisconsin. He served on the faculty of the Storrs Agricultural College and Connecticut Agricultural College as an instructor in Dairy Husbandry (1894-1904). After serving in a similar position at the University of Vermont, Beach returned to the College as its fourth president in 1908. Beach Hall was dedicated in his honor in 1929 a year after his retirement from the college. Charles Lewis Beach died 15 September 1933.
Beach, Charles L.
Biography
Charles Lewis Beach attended the University of Wisconsin. He served on the faculty of the Storrs Agricultural College and Connecticut Agricultural College as an instructor in Dairy Husbandry (1894-1904). After serving in a similar position at the University of Vermont, Beach returned to the College as its fourth president in 1908. During President Beach's administration, CAC became a college in fact as well as in name, offering its first four-year program in 1911 and granting its first bachelor's degrees in 1914. Beach oversaw a substantial increase in enrollment and started a major building program. He guided the college through the era of World War I, when it was dominated by the needs of military training, and defended it against strong criticism and attacks in the early 1920s. By masterfully presenting the college's case before the legislative committees, President Beach succeeded in maintaining the growth and improvement of the institution despite public hostility and indifference. Known to all as “Mr. Beach,” he was well loved from his quiet, friendly manner and his deep commitment to the college. Beach Hall was dedicated in his honor in 1929 a year after his retirement from the college. Charles Lewis Beach died 15 September 1933.
Scope and Content
The records consist of the general correspondence of the President of the College. It is the only extant collection of the papers of the president for this period. The correspondence is concerned with internal administrative matters, major policy issues at the college, with the college's relations with state and federal governments, and with other educational agencies and institutions.
The collection contains correspondence, reports, memoranda, forms, minutes, telegrams, blueprints, maps, fliers and published materials pertaining to the day-to-day operations of the institution from 1908 to 1928 (bulk 1920-1927). The small quantity of materials representing this significant time of growth and expansion in the institution's history is offset by the breadth of issues covered: information regarding programmatic changes and development to the location of screens for the windows of the president's residence, student suspensions and expulsions to faculty hiring and housing. A survey of this material reveals the changes in the functions of the President's Office during this period of growth from a small agricultural college to a larger, more broadly based institution of higher education. At the time of Beach's appointment in 1908, the laws and by-laws of the college specified that the president, subject to the direction of the trustees, had “the immediate supervision of all departments, and direction of all matters pertaining to the welfare of the college,” including the appointment and dismissal of all staff members and the designation of their duties. They also provided for the President's attendance at and participation in all meetings of the Board of Trustees. Few matters, regardless of significance, escaped the attention of President Beach.
As the college grew, more of the President's responsibilities were delegated to other administrative officers. The 1921 catalog states that, under the supervision of the President, “the three branches of the administration are managed by the Faculty, the Director of the Experiment Station, and the Director of the Extension Service.” Faculty committees relieved the President from the immediate administration of routine matters of internal government. During the 1921-1922 academic year, the college was divided into five academic divisions, each headed by a dean. The establishment of the offices of Dean of Women in 1928, Dean of Men in 1929, and Director of the Division of Instruction in 1931 were other important steps in the evolution of the office of the President, since each more clearly defined the duties of the institution's chief executive officer. By the time of the McCracken administration in 1930, the President was concerned chiefly with general policy-making, major campus issues, high-level appointments, and relations with the state and federal governments.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence ( undated, 1906-1929 ) is the largest portion of the collection and includes correspondence between the President's office and students, staff, faculty and the community on issues relating to the operation of the institution.
Series II: Notebooks ( undated, 1924-1927 ) include several folder of information about specific art collections and pieces collected in memory of Mrs. Louise Crombie Beach, the wife of Charles Beach.
Series III: Photographs ( undated ) contains photographs removed from the correspondence portion of the collection. Original locations of the images are identified with the separation form accompanying each image.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University and its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Custodial History
The records of the President's Office from 1908 to 1935 were stored in Gulley Hall until about 1960, when they were relocated to the attic of Beach Hall.
Acquisition Information
In 1968, the Beach Papers were brought to the Special Collections Department. They were transferred to Historical Manuscripts and Archives in August 1979. In 2001, the Presidential records were reprocessed and separated by presidential tenure.
Return to University of Connecticut, President's Office Records.
Administrative Records.; Administrator.; Blueprints.; College presidents—Connecticut.; Correspondence.; Educator.; Financial Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Publications.; School Records.; Speeches.; Universities and colleges—Administration.; University of Connecticut. Office of the President.; University of Connecticut—Presidents.
- Series I: Correspondence, undated, 1908-1928
  - Accrediting of C.A.C., 1926 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Council, undated, 1917 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Agricultural Bureau, U.S., undated (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Agricultural experimental stations in NE states, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Alsop, J. W. [Trustee], undated, 1924-1928 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Annual financial report, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Architects, 1927 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Athletics— Sumner Dole, undated, 1923-1925 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Athletic Conference, New England State College, undated, 1922-1926 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Athletic Council, 1927 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Attorney General, 1912-1919 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Blake, George, undated (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Board of Trustees of C.A.C., 1918-1921 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Brick, water absorption of, undated, 1925-1928 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Brick and data on waterproofing material, 1925-1926 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Brick buildings (waterproofing), 1925-1929 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Budget, 1920-1926 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
  - Buildings Department, 1926-1928 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
  - Buildings and improvements, 1925-1927 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
  - Buildings and water systems, 1922 (Box OS, 2:, Folder 20)
  - Building sites for faculty, 1927-1928 (Box OS, 2:, Folder 21)
  - C, undated, 1915-1928 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - Carillon, 1927 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Central Vermont Railway Company, 1925
  - Chimes— J.C. Deagan, Inc., 1927-1929 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - Church and Community House Fund, 1919-1924 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Church and Community House Project, undated, 1924-1929 (Box OS, 2:, Folder 26)
  - Church and Parish House, undated, 1919-1924 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - Church—Trustees, undated, 1926-1928 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - Civil Administration Code ( Frank Morgan), undated, 1921 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
  - Classroom Building, undated, 1920-1926 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
  - Classroom Building, 1927-1928 (Box OS, 2:, Folder 31)
  - Classroom Building—Clocks, undated, 1927-1928 (Box OS, 3:, Folder 32)
  - Connecticut Agricultural College, undated, 1920-1926 (Box 3:, Folder 33)
  - Connecticut Agricultural College Book of Views, 1915 (Box 3:, Folder 34)
  - Connecticut Agricultural College, Needs of; Preliminary statement prepared for subcommittee, undated, 1920, 1925 (Box 3:, Folder 35)
  - Consolidation of State Agricultural and Storrs Experimental Stations proposal, undated, 1915, 1925 (Box 3:, Folder 36)
  - Cultural Events, undated, 1917 (Box 3:, Folder 37)
  - Davis, I.G. (Tobacco), undated, 1925-1927 (Box 3:, Folder 38)
  - Draft Lists, 1917-1918 (Box 3:, Folder 39)
  - Dunham Funds, undated, 1917-1928 (Box 3:, Folder 40)
  - English position, Applications for, 1920-1921 (Box 3:, Folder 41)
  - Enrollment by students, 1922 (Box 3:, Folder 42)
  - Exams (Botany), 1909-1910 (Box 3:, Folder 43)
  - Experiment Station, 1925 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
  - Experiment Station—History and purpose, 1915-1916 (Box 3:, Folder 45)
  - Extension Department, undated, 1914-1919 (Box 3:, Folder 46)
  - Extension service, 1921-1922 (Box 3:, Folder 47)
  - F, 1919-1924 (Box 3:, Folder 48)
  - Faculty meeting minutes, 1927-1928 (Box 3:, Folder 49)
  - Farm products, 1919-1920 (Box 3:, Folder 50)
  - Filter beds and sewer system, undated, 1924-1927 (Box 4:, Folder 51)
  - Fire protection system, 1920-1926 (Box 4:, Folder 52)
  - Fisher, R.C., undated (Box 4:, Folder 53)
  - Forestry, 1914-1919 (Box 4:, Folder 54)
  - Fraternities, 1920-1926 (Box 4:, Folder 55)
  - Freshman lectures, 1916-1917 (Box 4:, Folder 56)
  - Fruit and vegetable storage building, 1925 (Box 4:, Folder 57)
  - General Assembly, 1921-1923 (Box 4:, Folder 58)
  - General Assembly, 1926-1927 (Box 4:, Folder 59)
  - Gilbert Farm, undated, 1914-1929 (Box 4:, Folder 60)
  - Graduates of C.A.C.—Positions held by, undated, 1912-1923 (Box 4:, Folder 61)
  - Graduates of C.A.C.—Positions held by, 1924-1928 (Box 4:, Folder 62)
  - Grange, 1928 (Box 4:, Folder 63)
  - Hall, Edward F. (Commissioner of Finance and Control), undated, 1926-1928 (Box 4:, Folder 64)
  - Heating Plant, 1915-1918 (Box OS, 4:, Folder 65)
  - Heating and Plumbing, undated, 1927-1928 (Box 4:, Folder 66)
  - Hicks Prize Essays, undated, 1906-1915 (Box 4:, Folder 67)
  - Housing, Requirements of, 1927 (Box 5:, Folder 68)
  - I, 1914-1915 (Box 5:, Folder 69)
  - Information sent to other colleges, 1919-1927 (Box 5:, Folder 70)
  - Insurance (College buildings), 1922-1928 (Box 5:, Folder 71)
  - Jarvis, C.D., 1914 (Box 5:, Folder 72)
  - King, Olcott F., 1921 (Box 5:, Folder 73)
  - L, 1914-1921 (Box 5:, Folder 74)
  - Land Grant Colleges, 1920-1928 (Box 5:, Folder 75)
  - Land Grant Publications, 1912-1917 (Box 5:, Folder 76)
  - Land owned by the college, undated, 1912-1928 (Box 5:, Folder 77)
  - Legislative Acts regarding college, undated, 1917-1929 (Box 5:, Folder 78)
  - Legislature—Background, 1911-1921 (Box 5:, Folder 79)
  - Legislature—Budget, undated, 1911-1921 (Box 5:, Folder 80)
  - Legislature— C.A.C. publications, 1915-1920 (Box 5:, Folder 81)
  - Legislature—Correspondence, undated, 1920-1921 (Box 5:, Folder 82)
  - Legislature“Pilgrimage” Executive Committee, [1920] (Box 5:, Folder 83)
  - Lighting system (campus), 1926 (Box 5:, Folder 84)
  - Longley, Raymond I., 1921-1922 (Box 6:, Folder 85)
  - Lowrie, Charles—Landscape Architect, undated, 1909-1913 (Box 6:, Folder 86)
  - Lowrie, Charles—Landscape Architect, 1914-1919 (Box 6:, Folder 87)
  - Lowrie, Charles—Landscape Architect, 1926-1927 (Box OS, 6:, Folder 88)
  - M, 1914-1928 (Box OS, 6:, Folder 89)
  - Manchester, Allen W., 1919-1928 (Box 6:, Folder 90)
  - Manchester, Harry G., 1918-1928 (Box 6:, Folder 91)
  - Mansfield Burying Ground Association, 1911-1922 (Box 6:, Folder 92)
  - Mansfield Questionnaire for School Children, 1927 (Box 6:, Folder 93)
  - Mansfield, Town of, 1927 (Box 6:, Folder 94)
  - Manter, Jerauld A., 1912-1925 (Box 6:, Folder 95)
  - Manson, Edith, 1918 (Box 6:, Folder 96)
  - Mathematics, Agricultural (Torrey and Dole), 1926-1927 (Box 6:, Folder 97)
  - Memorial Building, 1919-1920 (Box 6:, Folder 98)
  - Meredith, A.B.—State Board of Education, 1920-1925 (Box 6:, Folder 99)
  - Military Correspondence, undated (Box 6:, Folder 100)
  - Military Forms and records, undated, 1920-1922 (Box 6:, Folder 101)
  - Moreland, Wallace S., 1927 (Box 6:, Folder 102)
  - Moss, A.E., 1914-1928 (Box 7:, Folder 103)
  - Moss, A.E.—Report of the Forestry Department, 1915 (Box 7:, Folder 104)
  - Myers, A.J., 1923 (Box 7:, Folder 105)
  - N, 1921-1925 (Box 7:, Folder 106)
  - New England Land Grant College Association, 1923-1924 (Box 7:, Folder 107)
  - New York City Colony National Society, 1915 (Box 7:, Folder 108)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1903-1912 (Box 7:, Folder 109)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1913-1918 (Box 7:, Folder 110)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1922 (Box 7:, Folder 111)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1922-1923 (Box 7:, Folder 112)
  - Newton, H.D., 1918-1925 (Box 7:, Folder 113)
  - Nutmeg—regarding deficit and future policies and contracts, 1926 (Box 7:, Folder 114)
  - O, 1923-1926 (Box 7:, Folder 115)
  - P, 1909-1928 (Box 7:, Folder 116)
  - Parsonage, 1927 (Box OS, 7:, Folder 117)
  - Patch, R.H., 1921-1926 (Box 7:, Folder 118)
  - Pathological Laboratory, 1927-1929 (Box 7:, Folder 119)
  - Peck, Nellie L.—Resident Nurse, 1926 (Box 7:, Folder 120)
  - Perry, Delbert K.—Architect, 1917-1920 (Box 8:, Folder 121)
  - Perry, Delbert K.—Architect, 1921-1928 (Box OS, 8:, Folder 122)
  - Policy of the institution, 1921, 1924 (Box 8:, Folder 123)
  - Proctors, 1925-1928 (Box 8:, Folder 124)
  - Professors work schedule, 1920 (Box 8:, Folder 125)
  - Publicity committee, 1920 (Box 8:, Folder 126)
  - Purnell Bill, 1917-1927 (Box 8:, Folder 127)
  - R, 1920-1928 (Box 8:, Folder 128)
  - Radio Committee, 1923, 1926 (Box 8:, Folder 129)
  - Railroad (Storrs-Eagleville), 1907-1917 (Box 8:, Folder 130)
  - Refrigerating equipment (Dining hall), 1919 (Box 8,OS:, Folder 131)
  - Registrar, 1927-1928 (Box 8:, Folder 132)
  - Report ( C.A.C.), 192? (Box 8:, Folder 133)
    Scope and Contents note
    [photocopy of report associated with the "Pilgrimage" and in relation to materials located in 3:35]
  - Retirement, undated, 1919-1928 (Box 8:, Folder 134)
  - Retiring Pension, undated, 1916-1918 (Box 8:, Folder 135)
  - Reynolds, Charles, 1926-1927 (Box 8:, Folder 136)
  - Rhetoricals, 1906-1916 (Box 8:, Folder 137)
  - Rose, Ella J., 1918-1919 (Box 9:, Folder 138)
  - Rules and regulations—Firearms, 1914-1920 (Box 9:, Folder 139)
  - S, 1921-1928 (Box 9:, Folder 140)
  - Salaries of faculty, 1923-1927 (Box 9:, Folder 141)
  - Scholarship fund, undated, 1916-1922 (Box 9:, Folder 142)
  - Scholastic standing, Committee on, 1920-1922 (Box 9:, Folder 143)
  - Scoville, Robert, 1919-1925 (Box 9:, Folder 144)
  - Seckerson, H. A. (English), 1921-1925 (Box 9:, Folder 145)
  - Selective Service, WWI Regulations and Defense Message, 1917-1918 (Box 9:, Folder 146)
  - Sinnott, E. W., 1919-1928 (Box 9:, Folder 147)
  - Skinner, A. G., 1917-1927 (Box 9:, Folder 148)
  - Slate, W. L., Jr., undated, 1919-1925 (Box 9:, Folder 149)
  - Slate, W. L., Jr., 1926-1928 (Box 9:, Folder 150)
  - Smith, E. O., undated, 1911-1923 (Box 9:, Folder 151)
  - Snow, M. E. (accountant), 1919-1928 (Box 9:, Folder 152)
  - Southern New England Telephone, 1911 (Box 9:, Folder 153)
  - Speeches, Beach, undated, 1926-1928 (Box 9:, Folder 154)
  - Sprague, M. E., undated, 1920-1922 (Box 9:, Folder 155)
  - State Board of Agriculture ( L. W. Healey), 1920-1922 (Box 10:, Folder 156)
  - Statistics- State colleges, 1923-1924 (Box 10:, Folder 157)
  - Stemmons, Walter, 1917-1922 (Box 10:, Folder 158)
  - Stemmons, Walter, 1923-1928 (Box 10:, Folder 159)
  - Stevens, A. T., 1921-1925 (Box 10:, Folder 160)
  - Stoddard, Clifford I., 1919-1922 (Box 10:, Folder 161)
  - Storrs public schools, 1919-1921 (Box 10:, Folder 162)
  - Student affairs, undated, 1908-1922 (Box 10:, Folder 163)
  - Student affairs, 1923-1924 (Box 10:, Folder 164)
  - Student affairs, 1925-1926 (Box 10:, Folder 165)
  - Student affairs, 1927 (Box 10:, Folder 166)
  - Student affairs, 1928 (Box 10:, Folder 167)
  - Student aid committee, 1922-1925 (Box 10:, Folder 168)
  - Student Council and Senate, 1918-1925 (Box 10:, Folder 169)
  - Student enrollment - income cost/student, undated, 1909-1923 (Box 11:, Folder 170)
  - Student enrollment and other statistics, undated, 1921-1924 (Box 11:, Folder 171)
  - Student enrollment and other statistics, undated, 1925-1928 (Box 11:, Folder 172)
  - Student enrollment and student occupational data, 1922-1923 (Box 11:, Folder 173)
  - Student fees, 1927-1928 (Box 11:, Folder 174)
  - Student hours of instruction, 1921-1922 (Box 11:, Folder 175)
  - Student hours of instruction, 1924-1928 (Box 11:, Folder 176)
  - Student publications, 1926-1927 (Box 11:, Folder 177)
  - Summer school, 1920 (Box 11:, Folder 178)
  - T, 1916, 1925-1928 (Box 11:, Folder 179)
  - Tax Commissioner, 1922-1928 (Box 11:, Folder 180)
  - Tenney, L. B., 1921-1922 (Box 11:, Folder 181)
  - Torrey, G. S., 1919-1924 (Box 11:, Folder 182)
  - Travel expenses of faculty, 1924 (Box 11:, Folder 183)
  - Trumbull, John H. - Governor, 1925 (Box 11:, Folder 184)
  - U, 1922-1925 (Box 11:, Folder 185)
  - U. S. Department of Agriculture, 1912-1927 (Box 11:, Folder 186)
  - U. S. Department of Interior, 1921-1928 (Box 11:, Folder 187)
  - Vining, Roscoe H., 1918-1923 (Box 11:, Folder 188)
  - Water Commission - hospital and college, 1924-1928 (Box OS, 12:, Folder 189)
  - Water service and fire protection report, 1912 (Box 12:, Folder 190)
  - Wheeler, Charles A. - engineer, 1915-1918 (Box 12:, Folder 191)
  - White (Box 12:, Folder 192)
  - Wood, Walter C., 1927 (Box 12:, Folder 193)
- Series II: Notebooks, undated, 1924-1935
  - Macbeth Galleries, undated (Box 12:, Folder 194-195)
  - Art Collection Journal, 1924-1927 (Box 12:, Folder 196)
  - Louise Crombie Beach Memorial Collection of Art [see also Cultural Events], 1927-1935 (Box 12:, Folder 197)
- Series III: Photographs, undated
  - Photographs separated from correspondence, undated (Box 12:, Folder 198)